software engineering radio episode 21
error handling power tool
[Music]
welcome to a new episode of software
engineering radio this is part two of
exception handling on the microphones
are Michael and Arlo to start off our no
I think we discussed about two kind of
categories of exceptional conditions
could you explain them briefly yes well
actually it's good to start by defining
some terminology not that I'm into this
formalistic stuff but it's good to have
clear terminology for the rest of the
episode and to discuss exceptions or
exceptional conditions
well this distinctions really bought
whether exceptions or exceptional
conditions are expected or not expected
by the programmer and expected
exceptional condition is something that
you know about and that can occur and
that someone may might want to handle in
a way that a caller of your code might
expect that you want them to expect and
to handle maybe for example if the
network is down in a network call or the
database is down or someone passes in an
invalid name to your code then this may
trigger an exceptional condition that
you cannot handle or do not want to
handle in your code and you notify the
caller and expect the caller to deal
with it there's a chance of that sort of
you to document it as part of your
documentation of your class method or
subsystem or whatever and then yeah past
responsibility to the caller and the
second category well the second category
is things that are unexpected and it's
at first glance it's somewhat weird to
to even think about unexpected
exceptional conditions and notifying of
them the main cause of unexpected
exceptional conditions are of course
bugs or or just other exceptional
conditions that no one thought it for
things it is necessary to handle sort of
if this happens no one can really
recover from it who just make sure
nothing really bad happens shut down the
system that sort of thing
so this sort of restrict yourself to
handling expected conditions in a
well-defined way and then you have
unexpected kinds of exceptions that
you're sort of having handling the
catch-all way that's sort of make sure
nothing really bad happens but the
expectation is that it's not as but for
the system to behave as gracefully as
with the expected conditions actually
this brings me the story of my brings me
to an underlying problem of talking
about exceptional conditions of talking
about errors talking about problems and
software and that is this is one of the
softest topics in software engineering
handling errors is not really well
understood there are lots of different
definitions lots of different approaches
and there are very very few hard defined
rules how to do it how to do it well
yeah our recommendation here is for your
project or what we recommend here is to
separate the terminology and say
exceptional conditions that are expect
that you can't that you can kind of
expect are called errors and the truly
unexpected exceptional conditions are
than exceptions and this is not to
confuse with the chama language
terminology definitely java does not
distinguish these very well but this
distinction is really quite helpful at
the architectural level in thinking
about how to deal with it but well maybe
it's easiest to sort of dig into the
actual good stuff to take a closer look
at what you can actually can categorize
and how you can look at these exceptions
and that this I believe our model of the
levels of guarantee that have an impact
on the design and the the software
architecture yeah exactly
actually these levels of guarantee go
back to herb Saturn he documented them
in his book exceptional C++ and these
lumps of guarantee that we're about to
present um well go along the lines of
curb-sider it's not exactly his
categorization but it's
to it it's a very good book very
recommendable well the first and
fundamental level of guarantee is that a
piece of code guarantees that whatever
happens will be stable it can be cold
again after the problem
there will be no resource leaks whatever
happens um so I mean there is lots of
code out there that is not yeah
agree with this level of guarantee but
still this should be the fundamental of
the level of guarantee that basically
any code you have in production should
adhere to well let's look at these
different aspects of this level of
guarantee of this fundamental of level
of guarantee and think about what the
problems are if they are not met I mean
if there is an exception or if there is
a problem of any kind
and there are you there's a resource
leak so let's say a database family or
DUI handle or whatever maybe a socket
the thread whatever is lost this is a
for not making system resource that is
gone forever well at least as long as
the process lives which is bad enough so
any code must ensure this that whatever
exception collision occurs the resources
are freed there are different idioms and
different programming languages finally
blocks in Java
destructors in C++ every language has
its own means but this is really really
important whatever happens no resources
must be eat another thing is that is
more subtle is that the Greece that the
code that was called the the piece of
code that was called must be in a stable
State it's especially if well this is
the point of constructors if a
constructor throws an exception it means
that the object is not initialized and
it's not available this is part of where
the value of constructors that you
either have a fully initialized object
or no object at all but let's say you um
call it call it an initialize method
sometime later on and in the middle of
the initialization something goes wrong
some sort of error condition occurs then
you might have a partially initialized
the object even if there is no resource
leak this can be a problem if someone
calls it later on then um this might
cause any sort of undefined behavior
this is not part of the fundamental
guarantee the fundamental guarantees
says whatever happens the object must be
stable and callable in a well-defined
state sort of and it doesn't necessarily
have to do something useful it's
perfectly okay at the fundamental levels
guarantee if any further call just
throws another exception but it must be
in sort of in a well-defined state so if
I understood you right what do I really
know what do I really do with an when an
constructor fails I I will have an
unstable state and with that object
right so so what should i do then well
constructor there's typically no problem
because if the constructor reports
abnormally then the operation will then
be the language that you use ensures
that you do not get a reference to the
object well not on languages do it that
way so if the constructor fails with an
exception of some sort who does not have
an object at all that you could have a
pointer or reference to so if the
constructor fails there's usually no
problem
with the non callable object so might be
pro with moist for success it is
definitely no problem
with an uncalled object-- so I would
have a null pointer returned or
something like that well from a
constructor
if the constructor throws an exception
he don't get any pointer that is
returned and languages in for that you
do not have a pointer that can be
assigned to a variable so if a
constructor throws an exception the
languages be sure that you do not get a
pointer or reference they meet null or
whatever that you could be reference and
use to access the object later on this
is why initializing the object in the
constructor is such a good idea
if you want to meet the funnel and
fundamental guarantee of consistency
okay so this what's the first guarantee
the flourish level or guarantee yeah I'd
like to add an example in sort of
counterexample I'm from from the Java
world the hibernate persistence
framework is a bad example of this does
not deter this there the handle to the
database is called a session which is
the complex big object it has a session
cache first of all cache that on hood
where you can register objects and
hibernate documentation says whenever
any sort of exception occurs with the
session that could be optimistic lock
exception or whatever the documentation
says the session will be in an
undocumented state and you need to
discard it and start with a new session
this is sort of the opposite of what the
fundamental level currently says this is
bad design and hibernate
a good idea is to do it differently
ready let's go to the next level the
basic guarantee the basic guarantee on
hood on the fundamental guarantee but it
also demands that the object be usable
so it's the basic guarantee says yeah
there must be no resource leak and the
object must be in a well-defined state
stable State and it must be usable so
the fundamental guarantee permits you to
set a flag there was a problem and then
have a guard in every single method that
just throws an exception saying this
object is an invalid state it cannot be
used like now try em from try again
later does not make sense but use a
different object but the basic guarantee
says whatever happens if there was an
exception object is still usable this is
typically achieved for this this
guarantee is very often present if you
have stateless components in your design
because the stateless component whatever
happens completely with no visible state
can be call whatever happened the nature
is passed in data is passed through but
the component is callable again and
again and again and again so there can
be exceptions yes but they any exception
any problem an exceptional condition
that occurs will not invalidate the
component it can still be used this is
why statelessness is good for robust
code and
stateless components make error-handling
so much easier than stateful components
the third level of guarantee there's the
strong guarantee such as terminology and
the strong guarantee demands
transactional semantics growth back
semantics so if a call fails the strong
guarantee demands that the object
afterwards be in the same state the same
observable state as it was before the
core distinction between state and
observe an observable state is an object
might do some internal caching that is
not visible from the outside and
rollback semantics do not demand that
this internal caching be undone but any
visible state from the outside that is
not just for for performs optimization
um that must be rolled back and roll
back semantics are typically achievable
I mean they're they're often desirable
if you deal with with States because if
you do not have rollback semantics and
the caller needs to sort of catch the
who create a copy cache to the state
before he makes a call and then do all
this complicated stuff and it's far
better service of component of code to
do that inside the code that is called
so immutable objects are a design
practice that is very helpful to achieve
this sort of guarantee to achieve the
strong guarantee because I mean if you
have immutable objects whatever happens
can they they cannot have changed in
this state so if you have if you make a
call and any change just results in a
modified copy being returned then
obviously you have this rollback
semantics because the original wasn't
modified at all this is sort of the
simple case if you have seen single call
transactions sometimes it is desirable
to have explicit sorts of transactions
that span several calls with explicit
coming to rollback but once you go up to
that level comes more more complicated
and start implementing your own database
system you usually don't want to do
and especially in business systems a
typical design is that you have
stateless components at a business logic
layer and then the state is inside the
database and the database provides this
sort of rollback semantics which yeah
which makes it easy to easier to
implement that sort of trivial sometimes
to look for the components that are
above the database layer okay so this
was a strong guarantee and the next one
is the north roll guarantee right I mean
the no throw guarantee guarantees dust
but the name suggests
whatever happens you can rely on this
map on a method call not to throw
anything this is sort of very rare I
mean even if you have by well it's very
rare for languages like C sharp or Java
because basically whatever you call
could trigger and a trial here of the
virtual machine or an out of memory
conditional that sort of thing that is
sort of non-deterministic so this level
is it's also really necessary or helpful
if you deal with this sort of business
systems in Java or C sharp but it is
very important if you go down to closer
to the system to the operating system
inside the operating system nearer to
the machine if you do embedded systems
of some kind or if you implement a
database system but it's very important
that you have portions of code that you
can rely on not to throw anything but
the key point is not to achieve the
highest level of guarantee you can the
higher the level you achieve is the more
effort you need to put in doesn't pay
off but the key point is to think about
your design the terms of what guarantee
does my code provide or looking at it
differently what parts of my code you
need to provide which level of guarantee
to some these levels of guarantee are
the key thing is that the fundamental
guarantee should be provided by every
single part of your system whatever
happens you must not have resource leaks
and whatever happens you must not have
code that is an undefined state but
still available to climb
you should avoid these and then building
on that you can think about providing
the basic guarantee that says whatever
happens the components will be made
usable the strong guarantee I have
rollback semantics or for the throat
guarantee if you have want to have
portions that you can rely on that
whatever happens they deal with it
gracefully and contain any exceptional
condition I guess it will be really hard
listening to the discussion achieving a
know throughout guarantee for large
components of your system
well yeah it's certainly difficult and
oftentimes it's not necessary but well
then thinking of embedded systems that
are mission critical I mean I would hope
that a pacemaker that is in a heart or
that's the flight control system in an
airplane sort of provided you throw
guaranteed all right definitely are
there definitely is code for systems
even for larger components that must
contain every problematic condition but
yeah I agree it is difficult to achieve
and for many systems especially for the
typical business systems this effort
just does not pay off so going back to
our earlier terminology I assume that we
would call that they should only deal
with errors and repair things and and
learn how to deal with errors and that
there are basically no exceptions
in any case that is actually a good
question first of all it is true the
important thing is dealing with errors
in this guaranteed way I mean errors
just to recap errors were expected
problems and yeah these are the really
important things but then depending on
the situation especially when you have
mission critical systems that provide a
no throw guarantee it is a good idea but
there are situations where is a good
idea where it's necessary to deal even
with exceptions create gracefully so yes
usually you think only about errors in
dealing with errors when you design your
system and sort of shut
gracefully if there's sort of backdoor
things something but then you need to
think about if there's a bug how much
you liability what sort of behavior do I
need and sometimes this is possible and
even desirable to handle these as well
which brings us to the next thing I
think the next issue of architectural
concepts of dealing with exceptions the
single most important best practice of
dealing with exceptions is to handle the
exceptions at subsystem boundaries to
partition your system and only do
exceptions at these boundaries of the
system this might be if you have a big
monolithic system then you might just
have one component and deal with any
sort of exception at the at the GUI or
right below the GUI sort of popping up a
message box saying that was an internal
error I'm shutting down the application
gracefully for that was internal error
I'm not doing anything and let's hope
and pray that the system will continue
to run stabili or whatever but it is
important to not clutter your code with
catch blocks that handle exceptions all
over your code because this makes this
code unreadable and covers up the design
mix is very hard to understand what is
going on and also to sort of obliterate
what is really going on there so this
was your recommendation for exceptions
how about errors well for errors errors
are sort of different if you have an
error occurs sort of an expected problem
the expected part of the definition of
error means that you that someone
thought you might want to handle it
rather locally you might be interested
in and do you with it so if you can and
it makes sense for you then you can
should handle it as contain it and
handle it locally examples of this are
connection failover if the database is
down and one component says this
connection the connection is stale
database is gone you get an exception of
technical exception in our terminology
would be an error
you might try to reconnect to the
database or switch over to another
database with worse quality of service
characteristics or whatever or the
network is down you might in some
situations want to return data from a
cache or if there it was a call that's
what was to store data on a server you
might sort of put this call in a queue
just acknowledge it and send reduce try
to send it later this is a strategy
follow well this is the architectural
strategy of thinking about error
conditions and how you can gracefully
handle them locally this does not mean
that you always can't do that I mean
this founds failover of databases or
caching calls to a server if the network
is down yeah there are many systems
let's do that but then there are also
many systems that do not do that but
well that sort of makes these things
move these things from the error
category into the exception category of
unexpected things that you just sort of
treat as a back that sort of thing um so
this distinction is sort of not very
strict it's hard to keep up but if
things are in the error category with
you if they are intended to be expected
then you should do them locally contain
them retry or whatever if possible at
least think about that in your design
one important thing is you never just
catch an exception the technical
exceptions we do an error or an
exception never just catch it and hope
everything goes well which is one of the
big temptations of having checked
exceptions in Java because that you are
forced to deal with them in some way and
this sort of leads to this will really
bad practice of just catching and hoping
that no one would notice that is
definitely bad at here so either if
there if there there are exceptions the
unexpected just let them pass through
and hang them at SAP system boundaries
team boundaries from distribution
boundaries and if it is an error
condition you think about dealing with
it locally and would be cannot or do not
want to deal with it locally that you
can all don't let it go through and turn
them basically into exceptions okay I
guess then you have some rules of stunts
for us right exactly these rules of
thumb go back to the book wise Italy
about modern architecture they're not
exactly what is written in that book but
that book inspired these rules of thumb
the first rule of thumb is to separate
to distinguish between errors and
exceptions when you design a component
when you design a part of the system
with an interface that others would call
it is good to think about what are what
are the things that can go wrong and
which of these things would be
meaningful to a caller to deal with and
which wouldn't I mean it is it's good to
think about that but this shows that the
distinction is sort of hard to to get
exact because you will not know which
people will call you code how that will
evolve and some things are really hard
too hard to put in one of the categories
for example security if you have an
authorization check it is common
practice for an authorization check to
throw an exception if the authorization
fails is that an expected or unexpected
exceptional condition you sort of
expected that it can happen but then it
is we can happen everywhere every single
call can trigger this and you have to
handled locally so the handling is sort
of like for an exception that is at the
high level you cannot really deal with
it locally so this shows that yet is
good to think about this distinction but
it's then don't think about it too much
and try to be L restrict and applying
this distinction just will not work but
the key point is to give some sort of
documentation of what can go wrong in a
call what are the exceptions technical
exceptions come simplify what sort of
errors you might want to write the down
in API documentation or then optimize
automated tests for in whatever way but
yeah that should be documented in some
way another good practice rule of thumb
is to make your exceptions or errors
self documenting as we said in the first
episode on error handling there are
several different parties that are
interested in information about errors
first it is users
they are but they're easy to satisfy
mostly if something went wrong and is
not an error condition that it was
really meaningful for them that allows
them to interact their service get
something like internal error they find
with that but then you have armed system
administrators that are working with the
computers in the data center they need
specific information and the most
interested people that leave the most
detail are programmers so whatever
whenever technical sort of exception
thrown soon you find an error or an
exception it means that it should
contain all data that is necessary to
understand to reconstruct the context to
reconstruct what went wrong what led to
this and that all that isn't everything
that is necessary to handle this
exceptional condition which means that
often times exception classes have data
edits to them or you have an inheritance
hierarchy that reflects the way in which
they will be ended differently the key
point here is to hit the right level of
detail which is as always some difficult
but yeah some clove of detail is
necessary is very helpful for example
something some flags saying if the
server will be stable after this
exceptional condition or will be
unstable after the exceptional condition
that sort of thing is essential for
handling but then some people just
create a huge tree of exceptions of
inherit inheritance hierarchy of
exceptions and a very fine a very fine
granularity and then do not
differentiate in the handling this is
effort that is that doesn't pay off so
yeah you should make self documenting
exceptions but don't overdo it and that
kind of leads are ready to the third
rule of thumb to define exception and
error glasses only when necessary for
the control flow this means keep it as
simple as possible I guess I mean many
exceptions are handled and reported in a
very generic way often times just have a
catch clause that sort of catches most
exceptions and he'll just locks them
and pops up a message box to the user
saying there was an internal error and
notify the system administrator maybe
that he should restart the server
whatever there is no difference in
handling them and there is no point in
throwing different kinds of exceptions
just doesn't pay off and well there's
different cultures and different
programming languages but in many
languages there is sort of a culture of
aesthetically designing pretty much
effort into designing nice and complete
and huge exception classes this is often
just not necessary which means it is a
bad idea because of this effort that
doesn't pay off then another rule of
thumb is that technical exceptions are
often not the best technical way or
anyway they're not the only technical
way of reporting and exceptional
condition I mean often they are but then
return values are still present but
especially collecting parameter is a
great pattern for notifying of problems
in an easier way in more handy way than
exceptions are oftentimes collecting
parameter means basically you pass a
collection as a parameter to a method
and if something goes wrong inside that
method it just adds entries to this
collection for everything that went
wrong which allows to report several
problems collection a collection of
problems back to the corner where as an
exception it allows just one single
problem to be reported this is very
useful for example for brewing
validation in the user interface if you
have have a a dialog with two dozen
fields that say and you validate all
these have constraints on them then you
well badly design systems just throw an
exception in the in the checking code
the first check that fails was an
exception which is return to the user
interface and prints one message this
constraint was failed for example the
name field must be empty then you fill
that click commit again submit again and
then you get the next message that sort
of thing is bad design but it's sort of
the only kind of design you can do if
you use exceptions for reporting your
errors but there is very good practice
established practice to
as a collection through the validation
check and then have them add one entry
to this collection for every relation
that fails and when all the
relationships are through the new return
the whole collection could use interface
and display a whole list of things that
went wrong so exception throwing
exceptions is not the only way to report
problems to exceptional conditions and
it's good to keep that in mind
especially new design user interface
okay so the last rule of thumb the last
rule of thumb is robustness goes first
and performance tuning is a distant
second if even second maybe third or
fourth robustness goes first
this should be obvious it's been said so
often but still it is not obvious and I
hear that over and over and over again
people saying but using exceptions is
perform cost performance it's slow it
has a huge overhead so I will not use
exceptions but whatever usually trunk
codes because that's faster or I will
pre create an exception store that
exception have a never something goes
throw this pre pre calculated exception
this is weird this makes for brittle
code that can break easily found it
means that you get information that may
not be accurate in the report of the
problem I mean except for conditions are
rare or should be rare anyway and
thinking about performance in your in
the handling of exceptional conditions
is usually a really really bad idea
exception exceptional conditions are so
rare that usually it does not matter if
there's an overhead and using the
technical means of exceptions has become
quite fast by now yes it is slower than
a return code but that is just something
that does not matter at all no one
should care and if you do care about
that for example if you're in a bad
system then you might could at least
measure the impact it has if you have
measured and yes exceptions are your
bottleneck the bottleneck in your design
you might want to redesign and if you
all these means fail you might consider
moving exceptions or make the less
robust but simplify your design keep it
simple and then use exceptions and
exceptions make for robust and simple is
it the simple technical mean to keep
your code most of the code free from the
details of dealing with problems if any
other way of doing that is error-prone
its brittle so exceptions whose
exceptions and ignore performance
concerns in this part unless you want to
make do the effort actually measure if
throwing exceptions has the critical
impact on your performance which I
seriously doubt yeah I hear small
experience from my side
when I did development in the C++ for an
embedded system we actually measured
having the compiler include exception
code exception support code into the
generated binary and there we actually
had a footprint overhead and we had a
runtime overhead just by the
establishing the stack and then cleaning
it up again for exception handling so in
C++ at least there is some overhead but
as Arnaud already said to measure it
whether it matters whether it has an
impact on your application performance
definitely systems they're definitely
situations where you not want to use
exceptions especially in the embedded
world but yeah the point is measure and
probably if you're doing business
systems the overhead will not matter for
your system which brings me to UM one
way of looking at exceptions that is
sort of unusual but it's very helpful to
understand many of the issues of dealing
with the technical means of throwing
exceptions and that is exceptions are
really really complex I mean they are
simpler than error handling without them
but so exceptions are a non-local go to
and adding to that a non-local go to
twist through place you do not know and
if you look at exceptions this way it
will help you to keep your design simple
to use exceptions in an idiomatic way
consistently throughout your sister
to deal with this complexity use
exceptions wisely and make your
exception handling as simple as possible
because every ending is really really
complex ok disclosed our episode on
exception handling Michael would you
like to summarize this episode yeah ok
what I learned are that method calls
should always release resources that
they encounter any exceptional condition
so basically adhere to the fundamental
guarantee and is often desirable to have
even a stronger guarantee of that class
of the method that I'm designing so for
example have the the basic guarantee
that basically nothing went wrong and I
can repeatedly call that method again or
to even have a strong or no throw
guarantee API definitions should be
explicit about which arrows Darry
throw and when so this is a terminology
that the error that we introduced here
to refer to expected exceptional
conditions and finally Arnaud suggested
to catch exceptions always that
subsystem team or distribution
boundaries wherever there is a natural
boundary between subsystems or
components but preferably at a course
level not at a fine-grained level thanks
Arnaud for all the explanations thank
you Michael
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio the software
engineering radio team wants to thank
Henning party for providing the music as
well as lips and comm for hosting in
bandwidth for more information on the
podcast past episodes and feedback go to
s e - radio dotnet
[Music]